<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rows and Columns</title>
    <link>https://jlucasdba.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Rows and Columns</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2020 11:29:05 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jlucasdba.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Postgres Table Bloat</title>
      <link>https://jlucasdba.github.io/posts/tablebloat/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2020 11:29:05 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jlucasdba.github.io/posts/tablebloat/</guid>
      <description>One of the things DBAs coming from other database systems (like Oracle) need to be aware of when coming to Postgres is how Postgres manages changed data. This is covered in depth in a lot of other places, so I won&amp;rsquo;t repeat in too much detail. The short version is that when a row is updated or deleted, Postgres maintains the old version of that row within the table data file.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>https://jlucasdba.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 13:27:57 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jlucasdba.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>My name is James Lucas. I&amp;rsquo;m a database admin with 15+ years of experience; mostly in Oracle and PostgreSQL, along with some MySQL, MongoDB, and SQL Server work here and there. Other areas of professional interest are Linux system administration and tool development. The last few years I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing a lot of development work in Python, but I have a lot of experience with Bash and Perl as well. I&amp;rsquo;m also at least passably conversant in C, Java, and Go.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, World!</title>
      <link>https://jlucasdba.github.io/posts/firstpost/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 17:55:02 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jlucasdba.github.io/posts/firstpost/</guid>
      <description>So this is an experiment. I&amp;rsquo;ve never tried to do a blog before, and we&amp;rsquo;re going to see how it goes.
I&amp;rsquo;ve worked in tech a lot of years now. Every so often you come across an interesting problem or learn something new, and I&amp;rsquo;ve often thought it would be nice to have a place to write it up and share it with others. So that&amp;rsquo;s what I aim for this page to be.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
